<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GCDI | Connor M. French</title>
    <link>/tags/gcdi/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/gcdi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GCDI</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>GCDI</title>
      <link>/tags/gcdi/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>RStudio Cloud for Education</title>
      <link>/post/rstudio-cloud-for-education/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/rstudio-cloud-for-education/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.r-project.org/about.html&#34;&gt;R programming language&lt;/a&gt; is a powerful analytical tool that is commonly taught alongside applied fields like statistics, ecology, finance, and more. Efficiently integrating the language into a course can be difficult. For example, the time to set up programming exercises, troubleshoot technical issues, and follow progress can quickly eat away at time you as an instructor would probably like to spend covering course material. This is especially true in the current remote learning environment. The less setup and maintenance, the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt;, the company behind the popular interactive development environment, has a strong, free(!) solution. &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.cloud/&#34;&gt;RStudio Cloud&lt;/a&gt; allows teams to manage R projects in a common space. It is a way for team members (students, teachers, etc.) to collaborate, using the same set of software managed from a central location that the administrator, i.e. the teacher, has control over. The “central location” is a remote server hosted by RStudio that removes much of the headache from admin duties (and having to contact IT). This means that you can load all necessary files and packages into a central location and distribute RStudio sessions to each of your students without worrying about differences in operating system, versioning differences, etc. If a student has a problem, you can check on their project and even make fixes from your computer (with some restrictions)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of RStudio Cloud is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;project&lt;/strong&gt;. This is the fundamental unit of work. You store code, packages, and files here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;workspace&lt;/strong&gt;. This is where you create projects. Only you can access your project, but you can adjust permissions to let them be viewed and copied by other users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;private space&lt;/strong&gt;. This is critical for teaching! You decide who can access this workspace. Inviting and organizing to your private space is simple.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a detailed and readable guide &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.cloud/learn/guide&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;! If you are not quite sure this is for you, below is a typical use case, containing only the essential details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You first set up a &lt;strong&gt;private space&lt;/strong&gt; and determine who can access the space. As an &lt;em&gt;administrator&lt;/em&gt;, you can manage membership and can view, edit, and manage all projects in the space. When you add users to the space, their default position is a &lt;em&gt;contributor&lt;/em&gt;- they can create, manage, and edit their own projects. If you are fortunate to have a teaching assistant, you can change their permission to &lt;em&gt;moderator&lt;/em&gt;, giving them permission to view, manage, and edit all projects in the space. Note- administrators and moderators can edit other users’ projects, but they can only do this when the user has closed the project. Otherwise, you’ll get this error:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/connor-french/connorfrench/raw/master/content/post/images/disconnected.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You first create a &lt;strong&gt;project&lt;/strong&gt; within this space and populate it with files, packages, and code that you want students to access. When you are ready to distribute the project, you then change the permissions to allow everyone in the space access and select the option to make this project an assignment. Assignments make it easy for students to obtain their own copy of the project (this includes files, packages, and code), which they do by clicking on the assignments link. They can then edit their own copy, interacting with the R script exactly like they would on their personal computer. All users have the ability to download files to their personal computer if they choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The working environment for a user looks like a typical RStudio window:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/connor-french/connorfrench/raw/master/content/post/images/workspace_ss.png&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s it! There is plenty more detailed discussion of RStudio Cloud’s capabilities and options &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.cloud/learn/guide&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few notable limitations to RStudio Cloud. It is in beta, so there may be some instabilities. Feedback is generally positive, and most recommendations are to save often in case the session crashes, which is rare. The initial member limit for workspaces is 10 members, but all requests for more space are honored (anecdotally, classroom sizes &amp;gt; 100 students are possible). Each project copy is given 1 GB of memory and 1 CPU, so large data possibilities are limited. If your course requires large computational resources and you have these available locally or through a paid cloud service, &lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.com/products/rstudio/#rstudio-server&#34;&gt;RStudio Server&lt;/a&gt; may be another viable option. Development is happening rapidly, so more features will likely be available soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PDIG Training Grant Spotlight: Connor French</title>
      <link>/post/pdig-training-grant-spotlight-connor-french/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/pdig-training-grant-spotlight-connor-french/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;There are a lot of insects in the world. Like a lot a lot. Recent estimates put &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/24/7519.short&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;the number of insect species&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; at a whopping 5.5 million. Only about a million have names, leaving the other 4.5 million or so species undescribed. To put this into context, there are &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://amphibiaweb.org/amphibian/speciesnums.html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;8,053 described amphibian species&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; and the projected number of undescribed species remains in the thousands. While I consider all life to be equally important (and I’m particularly fond of amphibians- I mean, just &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?rlz=1C5CHFA_enUS832US832&amp;amp;biw=1343&amp;amp;bih=650&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=1&amp;amp;ei=6XpJXc7tOayv_Qac8oGQBA&amp;amp;q=ranitomeya&amp;amp;oq=ranitomeya&amp;amp;gs_l=img.3..35i39l2j0i67l2j0l6.53933.55501..55948...0.0..1.371.943.9j3-1......0....1..gws-wiz-img.ujvBzQEfoC8&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiOhpG-p-7jAhWsV98KHRx5AEIQ4dUDCAY&amp;amp;uact=5&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;look at these&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;), the gap in our understanding of insect diversity is especially concerning. They’re important for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nrcs.usda.gov/wps/portal/nrcs/main/national/plantsanimals/pollinate/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;agriculture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S0qm_L_HPdM&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;flowering plants&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fws.gov/midwest/endangered/insects/ambb/abb_fact.html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;decomposition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, and a host of other functions. Without a firm understanding of existing insect diversity, scientists can’t accurately determine the causes of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/2019/02/why-insect-populations-are-plummeting-and-why-it-matters/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;rapid declines&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; in insect populations across the globe. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Needless to say, describing 4.5 million species of insect is an onerous task. That’s why, as part of my PhD dissertation, I’m devising a new metric of diversity that skirts around this problem. Although I would love to go into excruciating detail about what it is, I’ll leave that up to my dissertation chapter. Briefly, I use &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/fact-sheets/DNA-Sequencing-Fact-Sheet&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;DNA sequences&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; from insects collected by researchers from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boldsystems.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;across the globe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; to summarize the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://b4fa.org/bioscience-in-brief/plantbreeding/genetic-diversity/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;genetic diversity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; of insect communities, rather than their species diversity. This makes data collection much more feasible across a broad scale. However, exactly what it tells us about insect communities is still uncertain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;wp-image-11278&#34; src=&#34;https://gcdi.commons.gc.cuny.edu/wp-content/blogs.dir/885/files/2019/09/bold_insects-300x150.png&#34; alt=&#34;Global map of insect DNA sampling intensity&#34; width=&#34;410&#34; height=&#34;205&#34; /&gt; &lt;font size=&#34;-1&#34;&gt; A map of insect DNA sequences deposited in the Barcode of Life Data System. Warmer colors indicate densely sampled areas. &lt;/font&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;To remedy this, I’m using &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://searchenterpriseai.techtarget.com/definition/machine-learning-ML&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;machine learning&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;. Machine learning, the part-statistics, part-algorithmic wizardry that helps Snapchat &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/cracking-the-data-science-interview/snapchats-filters-how-computer-vision-recognizes-your-face-9907d6904b91&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;turn your face into an alien&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; and Facebook &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://research.fb.com/blog/category/machine-learning/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;recommend you&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; custom underwear, can also be used to answer important scientific questions. In a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/news/2018/mar/12/what-is-biodiversity-and-why-does-it-matter-to-us&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;biodiversity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; context, machine learning can help clarify what about the environment, whether that is climate, topography, human-mediated habitat loss, etc., best predicts a selected metric of diversity. In my project planning stages, I decided to use this approach to assess the relationships my new metric has with other global-scale processes. However, I only had a rudimentary knowledge of the capabilities of a machine learning approach. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;That’s why I decided to take the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.rstudio.com/2019/02/06/rstudio-conf-2019-workshops/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Applied Machine Learning in R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; two-day workshop in Austin, Texas. The workshop’s goal was to “step through the process of building, visualizing, testing, and comparing models that are based on prediction.” This was exactly what I needed. Unfortunately, since it was a part of an industry conference for tech professionals, the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/conference/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;rstudio::conf2019&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, it was prohibitively expensive. Luckily, I was able to secure a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://digitalgrants.commons.gc.cuny.edu/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Provost’s Digital Innovation Training Grant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, which covered the costly tuition. As a University of Texas at Austin alumni, I easily found a couch to crash on, which cut expenses significantly. The prime location and generous help from the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gcdi.commons.gc.cuny.edu/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;GC Digital Initiatives&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; paved my way to the workshop. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;In between eating &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vaquerotaquero.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;street tacos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; and taking dips at &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.austintexas.org/listings/barton-springs-pool/4687/&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Barton Springs Pool&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, I learned the basics of performing machine learning analyses in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9kYUGMg_14s&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;R&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;, a programming language centered around statistical analysis. Going in, I had a strong background in R, but I did not have a working knowledge of machine learning. The workshop’s &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topepo/rstudio-conf-2019&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;exercises&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://resources.rstudio.com/authors/max-kuhn&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;strong leadership&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; gave me more confidence in using the machine learning techniques I was already familiar with and introduced me to algorithms I had never heard of. It was one of these new algorithms– I point out it’s named &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bradleyboehmke.github.io/HOML/mars.html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;MARS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; for the statistically and astronomically inclined– that I decided to use for my dissertation chapter. It strikes a balance between predictive power and explanatory ease that I am aiming for in my project. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;After some months of pulling my hair out, working through the kinks of how to wrangle 4.7 million insect DNA sequences, I was able to use my new machine learning skills to perform preliminary analyses of my data. The results, which I presented as a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/8nhvskh6xarg6ej/poster_ConnorFrench.pdf?dl=0&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;poster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; at the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.evolutionmeetings.org/evolution-2019---providence.html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt;Evolution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;font-weight: 400;&#34;&gt; conference in Providence, Rhode Island, point toward my metric being a useful summary of insect biodiversity. I received numerous bits of positive feedback that I am currently using to finalize my analyses and publish this work in a professional journal. Initially, I thought this project would take up a large chunk of my PhD, but with the help of the Applied Machine Workshop and GC Digital Initiatives, I was able to jumpstart my analyses and will put out a stronger product, sooner. In due course, I hope my research leads to a stronger understanding of insect diversity and how us humans are impacting it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
